All right, בוקר טוב.
Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is מ"ג Mem Gimmel and we pick
up at the bottom of מ"ב עמוד ב'. Mem Bais Amud Bais.
And אמר רבא, Amar Rava, four lines, five lines from the bottom,
last two words of the line. And if you remember we are
dealing with issues about
orifices or places in the body and the difference between בית הסתרים,
Beis HaSesarim, which is a place that is not the exposed skin,
it could be even a little as בית הקמטים Beis HaKemattim as
we're going to see which is like skin that's normally under a
fold, it doesn't even have to be in קמטים, Kemattim, קמט, kemet,
a fold, doesn't even have to be like interior like inside of
the mouth or something. And then there's בלוע Balua which is so
deep in that it's considered like it doesn't even exist anymore. And
let's take a look, the גמרא Gemara goes to that right away.
And sometimes of course there's a question where exactly you draw the
line, which was a debate of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava in
a number of important issues that we dealt with yesterday. So אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, five lines again from the bottom,
מ"ב עמוד ב'. Mem Bais Amud Bais.
שרץ בקומטו טהור נבילה בקומטו טמא. Sheretz bekumto tahor neveilah bekumto tamei.
Now the הלכה halacha is that some טומאות, tumahs, if you carry
them you're טמא, tamei, others only if you touch them. So the
טומאה, tumah, for example, of שכבת זרע shichvas zera and the blood
of a נידה, niddah, those things are only through touch. The טומאה
tumah of a שרץ, Sheretz, of a dead sort of rodent, those
that cause טומאה tumah only through touch. But the טומאה tumah of
a נבילה neveilah is even by carrying it. So now if you,
when's touch, if it's touching an inner place, a בית הסתרים, Beis
HaSesarim, an normally hidden place, not exposed, or even under a fold
that's not exposed because it's normally under a fold of the body,
then it's not considered touch. However, if it's being carried, then it's
not about touch. So even if you're carrying it, you know, inside
your mouth, you might not be considered touching it for halachic purposes
of טומאה, tumah, but you're carrying it. So that's what רבא Rava
says here. If it comes to a שרץ, Sheretz, a dead rodent,
which is only through touch, בקומטו, bekumto, if you're somehow touching it
or holding onto it through like a fold, like you know you
have like under your underarm or something like that, then טהור, tahor,
then you're טהור tahor because that space is considered normally like not
exposed and that is not considered a touch. נבילה בקומטו טמא, Neveilah
bekumto tamei, if however it's a נבילה, neveilah, a כזית kezayis of
an animal corpse, then טמא tamei you are טמא tamei because even
though it's not touch, you are טמא tamei for carrying and you
are considered to be carrying it. Now, שרץ בקומטו טהור, Sheretz bekumto
tahor, it explains. שרץ בנגיעה הוא דמטמא, Sheretz benegiah hu demetamei, a
שרץ Sheretz causes טומאה tumah only through touch, ובית הסתרים לאו בר
מגע הוא, ubeis hasesarim lav bar magah hu, and touching by a
hidden place is not considered touching. נבילה בקומטו טמא, Neveilah bekumto tamei,
but if the dead animal corpse is there in the fold, it
is טמא. tamei. נהי דממגע לא מטמא, Nehie demamagah lo metamei, it's
true that it doesn't cause טומאה tumah by touch, אבל במשא הוא
דמטמא, aval bamasah hu demetamei, it does by carrying and you're still
carrying it even if you're not touching it. Okay, שרץ בקומטו והכניסו
לאוויר התנור טמא. Sheretz bekumto vehichniso la'avir hatannur tamei. Now this is
relatively obvious, which is what the גמרא Gemara says. Let's say you're
taking this שרץ, Sheretz, this rodent, in your fold under your arm
or something like that and you walk into a huge walk-in oven.
In Fairway they have walk-in refrigerators or freezers. I wouldn't want to
walk into a walk-in oven, at least not when it's on, but
anyway, you walked in
there. והכניסו vehichniso what? Yeah, very good. Okay. והכניסו לאוויר התנור. vehichniso
la'avir hatannur. Now that is a כלי חרס, kli cheres, that's a
pottery vessel, and anything that's in its airspace is טמא. tamei. So
that case, טמא, tamei, you are טמא tamei because even though you're
not touching it, but you're it's in the, you know, it's in
the airspace of the תנור tannur and the תנור tannur maybe not
you, but the תנור tannur at least is טמא. tamei. Okay. Yeah,
not you because the תנור tannur becomes a ראשון, rishon, you wouldn't
be טמא tamei through the תנור, tannur, but at least the תנור
tannur is טמא tamei even though the שרץ Sheretz is here under
your arm. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא p'shita obviously. No, מהו
דתימא mahu d'teima אימא תוכו אמר רחמנא, aimat tocho amar rachmana, anything
in the כלי חרס, kli cheres, ולא תוך תוכו, velo toch tocho,
not in an in, and since it is considered not now, under
your arm it's not as obvious because here you could say it's
not touching an exposed part of your skin, but it's not like
inner, it would have been a more interesting thing to say let's
say it was in your mouth. That's like inner something, it's not
בלוע, balua, it's not swallowed, but it's inner. But anyway, קא משמע
לן, kamashma lan, that is still not, it doesn't matter, it's still
considered in. When we say in and not inside the inside, the
example would be if you had an oven and you had a
vessel in the oven and the walls of the vessel went higher
than the walls of the oven. Then it would be considered to
be in the inner container and not in the oven because the
inner container was not completely you know completely contained within the oven.
But here it would not, that would not be the case, and
A, maybe you are completely contained, and more significantly it seems that
B, being even if let's say you're higher than the oven, it
seems that this is not considered inner just because it's in a
בית הסתרים. Beis HaSesarim. Okay, so that would not be an exception,
it would still make the oven טמא. tamei. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar
Reish Lakish, so the oven was a little bizarre case but now
we're going to focus back again on this בית הסתרים Beis HaSesarim
issue and carrying versus touching. So says ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, קנה
בקומטו של זב והכניסו kaneh bekumto shel zav vehichniso והסיט בו את
הטהור טהור tahor. *veheisit bo et hatahor tahor*. Now if a זב
zav *zav*, now the normal הלכה halacha *halacha* is I'll tell you
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say in a minute but
just so you know going in normal הלכה halacha. *halacha* is that
when you touch something you're טמא tamei *tamei*, when you carry certain
things you're טמא tameh, *tamei*, the same way when you then when
you carry certain things also if you move them like you take
a stick and you move them טומאת היסט *tumat heiset* you're also
טמא tamei *tamei* and that's essentially normally understood to be like in
the category of carrying. So things that you're טמא tamei. *tamei* for
carrying you're also טמא tamei, *tamei* for like moving them even without
touching them. Now that's when you move the טמא tamei. *tamei* thing.
A זב zav *zav* is actually a person who is טמא tamei
*tamei*. What if the טמא tamei *tamei* thing moves you? Normally we
think about טמא tamei *tamei* as a dead thing so what would
be the example? But a זב zav *zav* is an example. Okay,
you could have another example that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
you're sitting in a huge seesaw and the טמא tamei. *tamei* thing
is weighing you down and moving causing you to be lifted up.
But normally the הלכה halakhah *halacha* is only when you lift or
move the טמא tamei *tamei* thing is not in the reverse. But
by זב zav *zav* we learn from a special פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
that even when a זב zav. *zav* moves you, you become טמא
tamei *tamei* even if he doesn't touch you. So let's take a
look.
Like a wheelchair?
Well, right, okay, right, or anyway in which he shoves you or
whatever. So אמר ריש לקיש *amar Reish Lakish*, קנה בקומטו של זב
zav *kaneh bekomto shel zav* if a זב zav, *zav* has a
stick in his you know under his arm let's say והסיט בו
את הטהור *veheisit bo et hatahor* and he pushes the טהור *tahor*
person through the stick without touching him טהור *tahor*, he's טהור *tahor*
because it's being carried in his בית הסתרים beit hasetarim *beit hasetarim*.
קנה בקומטו של טהור *kaneh bekomto shel tahor* however if you have
this stick under the arm of the טהור *tahor* person והסיט את
הזב *veheisit et hazav* and he moves the זב zav *zav* with
it טמא tamei *tamei*, he's טמא tamei? *tamei*. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama,
*mai taama*? So what's the reason? So the reason for the second
one is by the way as I said that טומאת היסט *tumat
heiset* is basically a form of טומאת משא *tumat massa*. So moving
somebody is like carrying them or moving something is like carrying it
and since if you carry a זב zav, *zav* you're טמא tamei.
*tamei* if you move a זב Zav *zav* you're טמא tamei *tamei*
and because it's about carrying it's not about touching it doesn't matter
if the way you moved it was through a stick under your
arm even though it's בית הסתרים *beit hasetarim*. בית הסתרים *beit hasetarim*
only matters when it's an issue about touching. So why you're טמא
tamei, *tamei* in the second case is what we've been saying until
now you are carrying something that causes טומאת משא *tumat massa*. You're
carrying slash moving a זב zav *zav* and therefore there's no it
doesn't matter about the בית הסתרים *beit hasetarim* issue. How about the
first case why you're טהור *tahor*? Let's take a look. מאי טעמא
Mai ta'ama, *mai taama*? What's the reasoning? דאמר קרא De-amar kra, *de’amar
kra* the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says וכל אשר יגע בו הזב *vechol
asher yiga bo hazav* anything that a זב zav *zav* touches וידיו
לא lo, שטף במים *veyadav lo shataf bamayim* and he does not
wash his hands with water. זהו היסתו של זב zav *zehu hesito
shel zav* from this we learn out that not only when you
move a זב zav, *zav* but when a זב zav *zav* moves
something because apparently we already know from other פסוקים pesukim *pesukim* that
if you touch a זב zav *zav* you're טמא tame *tamei*. So
why does it have to say if a זב zav *zav* touches
something? To tell me not only literally if he touches something but
even if the זב zav, *zav* moves something and this is the
only place in the תורה Torah *Torah* where the טמא tame *tamei*
person thing moving something else causes טומאה tumah *tumah*. Okay, so that's
what we learn from this. שלא מצינו לו טומאה tumah, בכל התורה
כולה *shelo matzinu lo tumah bechol hatorah kullah* that we never find
anywhere else in the תורה Torah *Torah* טומאה tumah *tumah* caused by
the טמא tame, *tamei* thing moving the טהור *tahor* but here we
learn it from the verse of anything that a זב zav, *zav*
touches and we say touch doesn't literally mean touch it means move.
But because it uses the phrase touch ואפקיה רחמנא בלשון נגיעה *veafkeih
rachamana belashon negiah* the תורה Torah *Torah* here refers to moving with
the verb touching. למימר *lemeimar* to tell you דהיסט ונגיעה כידיו *deheiset
unegiah kiyadav* that whether it is moving or touching it says וידיו
*veyadav* right וכל אשר יגע בו הזב וידיו *vechol asher yiga bo
hazav veyadav*. So it tells you that touching is with hands and
that maybe according to רש"י Rashi *Rashi* is the source where we
know the general הלכה halakhah *halacha* that touching טומאה tumah. *tumah* is
only by the exterior of your body not by the בית הסתרים
*beit hasetarim* because of the use of hands just like your hands
is also sort of exposed skin. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says we learn
that from somewhere else. But more significantly than the general principle that
touching is only the exterior for this הלכה halakhah. *halacha* we also
learn that the moving which we're learning from the word of touching
that when a
זב *zav* moves something the תורה *Torah* includes this new idea that
if a זב *zav* moves something he causes it to become טמא
tame. *tamei* it is understanding that this moving is seen as touching
by extension not as carrying but as touching by extension. So what
we actually have therefore are two concepts of moving. We have the
normal idea of moving טומאה tumah. *tumah* which is seen as a
form of carrying. By carrying there's no issue about exposed skin. By
carrying however you're carrying it I could be carrying it on my
back I'm wearing a shirt I could be carrying it with like
ten suitcases piled on my back right? I'm carrying it there's no
issue of exposed skin. So by carrying there's no concern of בית
הסתרים *beit hasetarim* when I am carrying the טומאה tumah. *tumah* and
as a טומאה tuma, *tumah* that has the טומאה tuma *tumah* of
משא *massa* that conducts טומאה tuma? *tumah* through being carried. When the
זב *zav* moves something that's not considered carrying right? When I move
the טמא tame, *tamei* היסט *heiset* is a form of משא *massa*.
When the זב *zav* moves something that is not a form of
משא *massa* that is a special חידוש chiddush. *chiddush* in the תורה
*Torah* and that is seen as touching by extension and since it's
seen as touching by extension. Only when he moves it through exposed
skin. But if he's moving it by carrying it in his underarm
or carrying it in his mouth, then it is not, then he's
not טמא tame because it's not as if he touched it. Alright,
so that is a special הלכה halacha that when a זב moves
something, it is a form of touching and it requires exposed נביאה
ראייה. neviyah reiyah. And this is in, this is like אחר יד
כאן. achar yad kahn.
No, no, no, no, no.
It's not אחר יד. achar yad. Okay, so now we, that is
the end of our discussion from yesterday about בית הסתרים and some
implications about that in places it doesn't matter, like when it's about
carrying. Now we go back to the משנה. mishna. And the משנה
mishna says that a woman's טומאה tuma. of bleeding is interior and
we have a lot of extremely important discussions about that and very
relevant להלכה. lehalacha. And now we're saying that the man's טומאה, tumah?
זב and בעל קרי, baal keri, is only when it leaves the
body. So let's take a look. אבל הזב ובעל קרי אינם מטמאין,
aval hazav ubaal keri einam metamei'in, but the זב and בעל קרי
baal keri only cause טומאה tumah when it leaves their body. זב
דכתיב, zav dechativ, by the זב it says, כי יזוב מבשרו, ki
yazov mibesaro, when it flows from his flesh. Right, by the woman
it said בבשרה, bivsara, in her flesh. So therefore it meant that
the flow is still inside of her. From the man it is
when it flows from his flesh, leaves his flesh, עד שיצא זובו
מבשרו, ad sheyetzei zovo mibesaro, only when the flow leaves his flesh.
That's not semen, that's the other type of flow. בעל קרי דכתיב,
baal keri dechativ, and the בעל קרי, baal keri, the seminal emission,
it says, ואיש כי תצא ממנו שכבת זרע, v'ish ki tetzei mimenu
shikvat zara, a seminal emission. So therefore it is about leaving the
body by the man and the flow within the body by the
woman. And now the משנה mishna goes on to give you a
very interesting case. האוכל בתרומה והרגיש, ha'ocheil betrumah vehirgish, a man is
eating תרומה terumah כהן kohen and he feels that his body is
like very sexually excited and somehow he's about to ejaculate, I don't
know how that happens spontaneously but whatever, so what he has to
do is he has to stop himself. Now he can still stop
himself because he's not טמא tame. until it leaves his body. So
the משנה mishna says he holds himself down, he holds down his
genitals so that he doesn't ejaculate and he swallows, and then after
he swallows and he's no longer eating or touching
תרומה, terumah, then he can let nature run its course. So that's
what the משנה mishna says. The גמרא's Gemara going to have a
problem with this and you might imagine what it is based on
the סוגיא sugya we've done a few weeks
ago. אוחז, ocheis, holding himself down, literally hold down his penis
essentially. והתניא, vehatanya, didn't we teach in a ברייתא, baraita, רבי אליעזר
אומר כל האוחז באמה ומשתין כאילו מביא מבול לעולם? Rabbi Eliezer omer
kol ha'ocheis ba'amah umashtin ke'ilu meivi mabul l'olam? If a man holds
onto his genitals, I mean literally his penis and he urinates, so
it's like he brings a flood to the world that leads to
זרע לבטלה, zera levatala, leads to him sexually exciting himself and the
seminal emission. So he even says a problem with holding yourself when
you're urinating. So how here can we allow this? It's going to
make things worse anyway. Meaning like two questions, like one question is
in general this is אסור, assur, but the other problem is how
does it make it better? It makes this problem worse if it
leads to sexual excitement. So the גמרא Gemara says what? The opposite,
he's trying to suppress it.
I know,
but the גמרא's Gemara assuming that any touch, you're right, you could
say it matters the type of touch which is essentially what the
answer's going to be, but the גמרא Gemara somehow assumes that any
touch will lead to it.
Why is it such a terrible כאילו מביא
מבול לעולם,
ke'ilu meivi mabul
l'olam, he's actually destroying
the world? Well that goes back to the whole דף daf we
had a few weeks ago. Destroying the world. I know, so goes
back to
because
it's based on the verse of כי השחית כל בשר, ki hishchit
kol basar, right, yeah this such a major...
it is the truth that it is the גמרא's Gemara as we've
learned in the beginning of כל היד Kol Hayad going way back
there to whatever דף daf it was י"ג, yud gimmel, that the
גמרא Gemara has a whole דף daf about the horrors of masturbation
based on פסוקים psukim, of כי השחית כל בשר ki hishchit kol
basar and I mean you're right, it's I mean look in, in
the זוהר Zohar for example, masturbating was a, is a, is the
sin that there's no תשובה teshuva for and is a worse sin
than having sex with a non-Jewish woman. So you're saying it's worse
than having sex with... Yeah, that's a general normative
הלכתי halachic step.
I understand, but you are correct that there's, but saying כאילו מביא
מבול לעולם ke'ilu meivi mabul l'olam is not a הלכתי halachic statement,
it's a rhetoric statement. But it is around...
I understand,
it's a construct the same... Yes, I don't see the need here
to compare it to the case of the underage girl which is
problematic in itself, obviously highly problematic, but it is true that the
גמרא Gemara is very concerned about masturbation and about זרע לבטלה, zera
levatala, probably inordinately to other
things. That is true. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
so how isn't this just going to make it worse and how
is it מותר? muttar? So
גמרא Gemara says, אמר אביי במטלית עבה, amar Abaye bemaltit avah, you
have a thick cloth. So you're holding yourself down but through a
cloth and therefore since it's not the touching of the skin it
does not cause sexual excitement. רבא אמר אפילו תימא במטלית רכה, Rava
amar afilu teima bemaltit raka,
even if it's a thin cloth and you maybe still feel a
certain amount of
not yet pressure but stimulation, so nevertheless כיון דעקר עקר. keivan d'akar
akar. Once the semen has... uprooted is uprooted, meaning that this is,
it's gonna come out of the body anyway. You're not causing it
normally; sort of touching oneself and masturbation causes the semen to, you
know, to go out meaning to collect and to go out here,
it's not changing what's happening, you know, whatever's gonna come out is
gonna come out anyway, you're not gonna cause more to come out
is essentially what he's saying. So it's not, you know, you don't
have to worry about it. And for the time and for the
time, well, maybe, it's a good point. Maybe otherwise it wouldn't be
effective. So, the מטלית matlit causes it to be effective temporarily, and
if you're concerned that it's gonna stimulate you further, no, what's, it's
already, the stuff that's gonna come out is already gonna come out
and it's not gonna make a difference. ואביי חייש שמא ירבה לסופה
Ve-Abaye hayish shema yarbe le-sofa and Abaye says,
no, I don't agree, I think that if you, you know, if
if it's too sensitive the way you touch yourself and it's not
through a thick cloth, then it's going to add, lead to more
semen coming out. ורבא לסופה לא חייש? Ve-Rava le-sofa lo hayish? Rava,
is he actually not concerned about that? והתניא ומתני בברייתא Ve-ha-tanya u-matni
be-braita למה זה דומה, le-ma ze dome, this is all what we
studied back in י״ג, Yud Gimmel, what is it similar to, touching,
a man touching himself? כנותן אצבע בעין, Ke-noten etzba ba-ayin,
like putting a finger into an eye. שכל זמן שאצבע בעין מדמעת,
She-kol zman she-etzba ba-ayin medama'at, as long as the finger is in
the eye, the eye continues to tear. So as long as a
man continues to masturbate, more semen will continue to come out. So
how can Rava say it's not a concern even if, you know,
even if he's already about to ejaculate, isn't it true that more
semen will come out if he continues to touch himself? So the
גמרא Gemara says, מדמעת וחוזרת ומדמעת, medama'at ve-hozeret u-medama'at, it tears and
continues to tear. ורבא, Ve-Rava, what would Rava say back? כל אחמומי
והדר אחמומי בשעתא לא שכיח. Kol ahmume ve-hadar ahmume be-sha'ata lo shekhiah.
To be heated up and then heated up again at the same
moment, right afterwards, that's not common. Now the way Rashi explains this,
he says it's a difference between, sort of, you know, after a
person has, a man has ejaculated, that then to say that he
will have, it will happen again right afterwards, he'll be able to
ejaculate again right afterwards, that is not to be concerned about. And
for some reason Rava says that we're not concerned that the touching
himself at this moment will cause it to be increased right now.
It's only a concern of whether it will happen afterwards and he's
not concerned that it will happen immediately afterwards, that, you know, that
he can get excited again like that right after. And he's not
concerned right now that it will add to it because he assumes
that since it's about to happen, anything that's going to come out
at this moment, it's already defined. And if we're talking about more
excitement that it'll only be afterwards and that he's not concerned will
happen again. So that is the debate of Abaye and Rava, how
much you have to concern that when it's ממש mamash at this
stage, that physically touching or touching not through a thick cloth will
lead to, you know, will lead to it, to him ejaculate even
further. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel,
now everybody can stop being uncomfortable. אמר שמואל: כל שכבת זרע שאין
כל גופו מרגיש בה אינה מטמאה. Amar Shmuel: Kol shikhvat zera she-ein
kol gufo margish bah eina metame'at.
Any semen that does not lead, if it's still a little uncomfortable
but not as much, any semen that does not come out when
the entire body is excited, meaning if it somehow like dribbles out
and it's not through a case of the body being heated up
or sexual excitement, then it does not actually cause טומאה. tumah That's
pretty amazing. This is semen. So
it would be זרע, zera, not זב. זרע, zera, but it doesn't
come out through sexual excitement. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, yeah.
זב is a זיבה, ziva,
it's a different, no, I know,
this is actual semen, but it does not cause
טומאה.
tumah. מאי טעמא, how would it happen without any sexual excitement? I
mean, it's not like you're just walking one day and then it
just comes out.
Yeah, but it sometimes can happen if you, you know, I mean,
it can happen, it can happen, it can happen. Okay. מאי טעמא,
what's the reason? שכבת זרע אמר רחמנא, Shikhvat zera amar Rahmana, because
it says literally a line of seed, so בראויה להזריע, be-ra'uyah le-hazri'a,
which means that it can cause a conception. And he understands that
even if the semen comes out, if it's not coming out as
a result of sexual excitement, it does not have the ability to
lead to conception. Now, obviously that's not true,
but it might be that it's not coming out with a powerful
enough sort of ejaculate that it would get into the woman's uterus.
I mean, nowadays you could, you know, you'd use a turkey baster
or other ways of getting it in, even if, some people actually
do their own
homemade artificial insemination, I'm serious, you don't even need to go to
a doctor. But anyway, but here it sounds like the quality of
the semen does not have the ability to cause conception, which is
how what he understood, and he understands that in that case it
does not cause, it does not cause טומאה. tumah So let's take
a look. מיתיבי, Metivei, they ask on this. היה מהרהר בלילה ועמד
ומצא בשרו חם, Haya meharher ba-laila ve-amad u-matza besaro ham, a man
had, you know, sexual thoughts at night, and he woke up and
he found that his, literally his flesh, but it means, you know,
his genitals, were hot, so טמא, tamei. he's tameh, he has to
assume that he ejaculated in the middle of the night even though
he can't find it, but you combine the factors and it seems
that that's what happened. So anyway, how does this work for Shmuel?
According to Shmuel, it had to come... It couldn't have just dribbled
out. So the גמרא Gemara assumes that if it came out through
a real sort of like seething, that the body was really excited
or
whatever, he would have been aware of it. So the גמרא Gemara
says תרגמה רב הונא במשמש מטתו בחלומו Targema Rav Huna bemishamesh mitato
bachalomo דאפשר לשמש בלא הרגשה, de’efshar leshamesh belo hargasha, that basically he
dreamed that he was having sex. So since he dreamed he was
having sex, he obviously was having the type of excitement. And the
question is how can he have had that excitement without being aware?
And the basic answer is he had the excitement and it was
translated in his dream as if he was having sex. So he
actually did have the feeling even though he wasn't conscious of the
feeling at
the time. Right. Otherwise, so right, that's the אוקימתא. ukimta. It's saying
במשמש מטתו בלילה. bemishamesh mitato balayla. It's limiting it to a case
where that was the dream. Now again, I don't even know why
you have to say that. If a person is dreaming, you can
have a lot of sensations of your body. I mean, first of
all, we know that's true, right? You know, that it'll be that
when things are things that are sensations of your body, you incorporate
them into your dream. Right. But it's possible that your body has
a sensation that maybe you're not even translated into your dream and
it's still a sensation of your body. So it's not exactly clear
why the גמרא Gemara had such a hard time understanding that how
could this happen at night without you being aware? But the answer
is okay, you were aware, you incorporated it into your dream and
so on. Now, I do want to say something by the way,
that the emphasis here is the word
הרגשה. hargasha. Right, the first statement was אין גופו מרגיש, ein gufo
margish, which is more like a
descriptive, your body is not sensing, is not feeling what's happening. So
you're not sort of, you don't have the sensation. Then it translates
here into more of a noun and it says בלא הרגשה, belo
hargasha, without הרגשה, hargasha, without sensation. Not your body isn't sensing, but
sensation. Why is that significant? It's only significant because we're going to
see when we get to a later discussion by women and their
טומאה, tumah and a similar position of שמואל, Shmuel, that שמואל Shmuel
says when blood comes, he adds a criteria that we have not
seen at all until now and it has a profound, profound implication
for הלכות נדה, Hilchos Niddah, that when blood comes out of a
woman, she's not טמאה tameia unless it is accompanied with הרגשה, hargasha,
with some sense of sensation. And what's important to know here is
that it is the same שמואל Shmuel that is saying for a
man that when semen comes out of the body, it does not
cause טומאה tumah unless it is accompanied with sensation. And now the
question is, ah, what about the night? So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, you had the sensation and you weren't aware of it or
you incorporated it into your dream and so on. And we'll talk
about women as well, but the use of the phrase of הרגשה
hargasha and thinking about the parallel, and these are both statements of
שמואל, Shmuel, are very significant. שמואל Shmuel is saying it is not
just about a fluid exiting your body. It's about a real type
of an experience and therefore it is with an accompaniment of הרגשה.
hargasha. Okay, so let's take a look now. The גמרא Gemara has
a slightly different version of שמואל. Shmuel. Yes.
It moves it from like an objective analysis and makes it a
subjective analysis and that is absolutely correct and it relocates,
you know, the whole experience. When we just learned מסכת נדה, Masechet
Niddah, we spoke a bit about the sort of objectification, which is
a necessary part of הלכה. halacha, And that's been sort of a
running theme here throughout, you know, sort of objectifying the woman, I
mean if it was about a man it would be objectifying the
man, in some things we have that about a זב, but mostly
this is about a woman, you know, and us looking and determining
what things happened and is she טמאה. tmeia. And turning into a
criteria of הרגשה hargasha very much restores the subjective reality. How do
you then determine it להלכה lehalacha is a really important question. But
that is very significant in שמואל Shmuel both by a man and
by a woman and we'll see it by a woman a little
later. So let's take a look.
Yeah, wouldn't there be a difference between a ספק טומאה safek tuma
and a ודאי טומאה vaday tuma because that was what you do
for טומאה? tumah Yes. So that doesn't enter into this discussion. You
mean why couldn't the answer be ספק טמא? safek tamei? It could
be. The phrase was because it says that because
I mean first of all it says you're having sexual thoughts and
he woke up
with his whole genital area heated up.
So assumes that those combined are enough of an indication to treat
it as a ודאי. vaday. You know, that was partly the question
because it said he's ודאי טמא. vaday tamei. How could you say
ודאי? vaday? So, okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
לישנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, another version of שמואל's Shmuel statement is the
following. אמר שמואל כל שכחוזר שאינו יורה כחץ. Amar Shmuel kol shechozer
she’eino yoreh kacheitz. It's not just that you have some type of
a sensation that is coming out. It's actually how it comes out
as well. It has to be literally being like shot like an
arrow, coming out with a powerful stream. If it doesn't do that,
אינו מטמא, eino metamei, it doesn't cause טומאה. tumah Because presumably that
also does not lead to conception. Now here, the תוספות I think
makes this point explicitly. It's not that the semen cannot impregnate, but
it is that it won't get where it needs to get if
it's not coming out that way. So
this is actually an even bigger חידוש. The Torah says שכבת זרע.
shichvat zera. right, semen. שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* says, well, it's only semen
that has the potential of leading to conception. Now, we might disagree
with שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*'s science, but at least in that case, he's
describing one type of semen as opposed to another, a quality of
the semen. And he thinks that if it comes out without sensation,
it is of a different quality. But here, he's saying even if
it has the quality that it can cause sensation, you know, it
can cause insemination, it can cause conception, if it's not coming out
in a way that would lead to that, then even that is
not זרע zera *zera* that causes טומאה tumah. *tumah*, which is quite
fascinating. You might want to say the man is not a בעל
קרי ba'al keri *baal keri*. If it's about being a רואה ro'eh
*roeh* rather than being a נוגע nogei? *nogea*, you could describe the
act, you know, the process that happened to the body. But to
say that the semen itself does not cause טומאה tumah, *tumah* because
of how it came, even if the quality of it is the
same, seems to be a tremendous חידוש *chiddush*.
And that's where he is not טמא tamei, *tamei*?
Yeah, correct. He's not טמא tamei. *tamei* and the semen is not
טמא tamei, *tamei*. Okay, so מאי איכא בין האי לישנא והאי לישנא
*mai ika bein hai lishna ve-hai lishna*? Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, what's the difference between the two approaches? Either way, presumably if
you need there to be a sensation in the body, it means
it's coming out in a powerful way, it's not just dripping out.
So aren't those essentially the same case? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, no. איכא בינייהו נעקרה בהרגשה ויצאה שלא בהרגשה *ika beinaihu ne'ekra
behargasha veyatza shelo behargasha*. No, that he had a sensation as it
was coming out, so there was a sensation, but then it came
out, it just, you know, sort of dribbled out. So there was
a sensation as part of the process, but not when it actually
came out and it didn't come out in a powerful stream. Does
ההלכה *ha-halacha* פסקן *pasken* this way? Yeah, basically.
So they say like a בעל קרי ba'al keri, *baal keri* for
instance אסור assur בתלמוד תורה *assur be-Talmud Torah*, so it would, right?
Yeah, we're not going to...
we'll discuss that when we get to ברכות *Berachos*. Okay, and so
anyway, so let's take... so okay, so that's his הלכה halacha *halacha*.
And so the question is, is just the הרגשה hargasha *hargasha* at
the beginning of the process or does it need to be throughout,
which ultimately leads to it coming out as a stream? So now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, מילתא דפשיטא ליה לשמואל מבעיא
ליה לרבא *milta de-pshita leh le-Shmuel miba'ya leh le-Rava*. This issue which
was obvious to שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* was a question that רבא Rava,
*Rava* asked. איבעיא רבא Rava *iba'ya Rava*. רבא Rava *Rava* asked: נעקרה
בהרגשה ויצאה שלא בהרגשה *ne'ekra behargasha veyatza shelo behargasha*. It was uprooted,
you know, the process began with a sensation, but then when it
came out of the body, it came out without a sensation. מהו
mahu?
*mahu*? What's the הלכה halacha, *halacha*? So we just said that according...
I mean it was פשיטא *pshita* to שמואל *Shmuel*, we just don't
know which way because there were two versions of what שמואל *Shmuel*
said. But anyway רבא *Rava* asked the question. מהו mahu? *mahu*? What's
the הלכה halacha, *halacha*? תא שמע Ta shema, *ta shema*, come and
hear. בעל קרי ba'al keri, שטבל ולא הטיל מים *baal keri she-taval
velo hetil mayim*. So a בעל קרי ba'al keri, *baal keri* went
to the מקוה mikveh *mikvah* but he had not urinated beforehand. Now
לכשיטיל מים טמא tamei. *lich-sheyatil mayim tamei*. When he urinates he's טמא
tamei. *tamei* because we assume with this urine will come out little
drops still of the semen. Now that semen is not coming out
through the type of normal stream of semen. It's coming out... it's
like it dribbled out because it's not coming out with that type
of an ejaculation. So in that type of a... you see therefore
that even if it comes out שלא בהרגשה *shelo behargasha*, so what
do you do with that? שאני התם דרובה בהרגשה נפיק *shani hatam
de-ruba behargasha nafik*. No,
since there it's just the remnants of a seminal emission and the
process... and when the ninety-five percent came out, it came out with
הרגשה hargasha *hargasha*, it came out with the stream, this stuff that's
later is considered to be part of that. Again, this is so
bizarre, right? Because normally you assume that it's a question about the
quality, about the זרע *zera* causes טומאה tumah *tumah*. And now we're
talking much more about the process, the act of how it came
out of the body, even if it's the same semen. To the
point that we can say that if the process started before, here
a day later some leftover semen from yesterday's process, that's going to
be טמא tamei. *tamei* because of what happened yesterday. Not based on...
you know, and that's going to define the quality of what we're
dealing with today. So it is quite a, you know, different way
of looking and obviously it's much more about רואה *roeh* and about
emphasizing the process that happened to the man.
Does the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* agree with
this too?
בעל קרי keri שטבל ולא הטיל מים *baal keri she-taval velo hetil
mayim*. This is a משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*, yeah, everybody would have to
agree with it. לישנא אחרינא *lishna achrina*. So that's version number two.
לישנא אחרינא *lishna achrina*, version number three. אמרי לה *amri leh*. אמר
שמואל Amar Shmuel, *amar Shmuel*.
So here's the third version. כל שכבת זרע shichvat zera שאינו יורה
כחץ *kol shikvas zera she-eino yoreh ke-chetz*, if the semen does not
come out shot like an arrow, אינו מזריע *eino mazria*. It does
not lead to insemination. It does not lead to conception. מזריע הוא
דלא מזריע *mazria hu de-la mazria*. Right, it does not lead to
insemination. הא טמויי מטמי *ha tamuyei matmei*. But it would cause טומאה
tumah, *tumah*. שנאמר she-ne'emar כי יהיה בך איש אשר לא lo, יהיה
טהור מקרה לילה *shene-emar ki yihyeh be-cha ish asher lo yihyeh tahor
mi-kreh layla*. If there's a man that's not טהור *tahor* because of
an event of night. אפילו קרי בעולם *afilu keri be-olam*. Any מקרה
*mikreh*, any occurrence, any way that the semen came out. So this
way it sort of rejects everything we said before and basically if
no matter how it comes out, it causes טומאה tumah *tumah*. Okay,
so those were three very fascinating approaches about it, but certainly two
of the three emphasize that it's not enough that it's semen, it
has to be בהרגשה *behargasha*. ובהרגשה *ve-hargasha* just at the beginning or
beginning and the end? And that as I said is very important
because שמואל *Shmuel* says something almost identical by women which we will
see. And as David said, frames it much more not about the
object, about the thing, the fluid, but about the process and also
very much locates it much more subjectively rather than purely objectively.
Okay
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. בעי רבא, ba'ei Rava,
רבא asked,
עובד כוכבים oved kochavim שהרהר, she-hirher, so a non-Jew had a sexual
thought and the semen was sort of like in the process of
coming out, so you had the עקירה akira what the גמרא Gemara
referred to before, the uprooting, that it is now sort of in
the process, but it has not yet come out of his body,
וטבל ve-taval and he went to the מקוה mikveh. not לטהר le-taher
to become a Jew. Okay, so this is what we are thinking
about. Exactly. Well, you know, maybe it was one of those cases
where he was converting for the sake of marriage, who knows.
Anyway, well, plus it is not אסור assur for a non-Jew to
masturbate.
Right, there you go too. So anyway, actually there is some debate
in the אחרונים achronim about that. Anyway, so, okay, so מהו? So
here is the point is that when it was עוקר, oker, it
was not yet טמא tamei, because he was a non-Jew. When it
came out he is a Jew. So before we were discussing the
importance of the beginning of the process and הרגשה hargasha at the
beginning of the process and so on, is that beginning of the
process needed to cause טומאה? tumah Let's take a look. אם תמצא
לומר בתר עקירה אזלינן, im timtza lomar batar akira azlinan, if you
say you go by the עקירה akira when the process begins, and
that if there was no הרגשה hargasha, there you are okay, so
הני מילי hani milei I am sorry, or if excuse me if
there was הרגשה hargasha. there it is a problem even if it
came out without הרגשה, hargasha right that was one possibility, as long
as it was עוקר oker with הרגשה. hargasha So הני מילי לחומרא,
hani milei le-chumra, that
is to be strict, that we would say even if it comes
out dribbling, if it was עוקר oker with הרגשה hargasha it is
enough to be טמא. tamei אבל הכא לקולא, aval hacha le-kula, here
to be lenient and say because there was no הרגשה hargasha that
was halachically meaningful, excuse me, no עקירה akira that was halachically meaningful
it should not be טמא, tamei. that we wouldn't be say לא
אמרינן, lo amrinan, we wouldn't say. או דילמא לא שנא, o dilma
lo shana, or maybe it doesn't matter. תיקו. teiku. So the גמרא's
Gemara basically the way it is framing it obviously it is like
a hypothetical case, but it is asking a conceptual question. We have
given weight to the beginning of the process,
what we call עקירה. akira. On the other hand, it is actually
quite fascinating that we gave weight because if you think about it
in the משנה Mishnah we know that the טומאה tumah of a
בעל קרי is only when it leaves the body, and nevertheless we
have now given some significance to the beginning of the process and
saying הרגשה hargasha, at the beginning is significant. Now what we want
to know is, would we be able to give significance just to
the end? If somehow the beginning of the process was not meaningful,
let's say no הרגשה hargashah. or let's say he was a non-Jew,
but the end of the process was with הרגשה, hargashah so we
have given weight to the beginning, would we also give equal weight
to the end, the ביאה bi'ah itself? And that's the conceptual question
he is asking and it does not have an answer.
So they're not questioning the conversion itself. Right, no, he is sexually
excited, right, he
is not thinking about God and the מצוות. mitzvot.
I am not sure why I should go out and have crab
right before my conversion.
Well, it doesn't mean that at the moment that you are converting
you were thinking about God, you were thinking about crab when you
went to the טבילה? tevilah? For what reason?
Because it's my last chance.
Oh, was that your last supper? Nothing אסור at all for a
non-Jew yet. All right. בעי רבא, ba'ei Rava: רבא asked.
זבה, zava, now we are back to women. זבה שנעקרו ממי רגליה.
zava she-ne'ekru mimei ragleha.
Now that's just nice now.
Right, now, now you will remember that
now by a זבה zava these questions are less possible because by
a זבה zava and a נדה niddah the טומאה tumah is inside
the body, so where you going to sort of draw these similar
types of lines of distinctions? But we do have another type of
a fluid, right, the מעיינות ma'ayanot of a זב and a זבה,
zava the urine and other types of fluids, once a woman's already
a זבה zava, or a נדה niddah or a man's a זב,
those also are a source of טומאה. tumah. And those presumably are
when they leave the body. So we are going to have a
similar type of a discussion. Let's take a
look. זבה zava שנעקרו ממי רגליה. she-ne'ekru mimei ragleha. So a זבה
zava basically, you know, literally the urine was uprooted. And you understand
exactly the sensation the גמרא's Gemara discussing, right? It means like you
know you feel you've got to go to the bathroom. That's what
it means uprooted, that was a similar point about the שכבת זרע
shichvat zera that it hasn't come out yet but it's in the
process, it's there, waiting to come out. So basically,
she has, so she has to go to the bathroom, she has
to urinate. וירדה וטבלה, ve-yarda ve-tavla, and she goes into the מקוה.
mikveh Now by the way, they say you are not supposed to
go into the מקוה mikvah, when you have to urinate because then
you hold your body differently and the water doesn't all get to
all the exposed places, but that's a more of a לכתחילה. lechatchila.
So this is not a concern, no this is not for גירות,
geirut, this is for being a זבה. zava. מהו? What do we
say? Halachically, halachically. אם תמצא לומר בתר עקירה אזלינן, im timtzo lomar
batar akirah azinan,
do you go
when it gets uprooted? So הני מילי שכבת זרע דלא מצי נקטיה,
hani milei shichvat zera dela mitzi naktei,
maybe that is by the semen, because basically you can't really hold
that back, you know you have to push down and it is
very hard to hold back for any amount of time. So there
we would say that even the uprooting is considered to be part
of the process because it's almost from the moment it uproots till
it comes out, you really can't interrupt that process. אבל aval מי
רגליה, mei raglehah,
but when it comes to urine, דמצי נקיט לה, dematzi nakit lah,
that it's possible to hold it in, as anybody who's been on
a long road trip knows, right? לא, then maybe we don't say
the uprooting is as significant because it's more detached. או דילמא לא
שנא, o dilma lo shanya, maybe it doesn't matter. Which basically means
what is the question? So the question is like this...
hold on one second...
Right, so do we say that the urine that was נעקר, ne'ekar,
that became ready to come out when she was a זבה? zavah?
Right, we say the urine of a זבה zavah is טמא. tamei
But when is the urine of a זבה zavah טמא tamei is
essentially what we're asking. When it comes out of her body or
when it's נעקר? ne'ekar? What difference does it make? Because once she
goes to the מקוה, mikvah between when it's נעקר ne'ekar and when
it comes out. So if it's טמא lo tamei. when it was
נעקר, ne'ekar, then it's been טמא tamei urine in her body and
now it came out even after the מקוה mikvah and the urine
is טמא. Tamei If it's only טמא Tamei when it came out,
well when it came out she's not a זבה zavah and it's
טהור. That's the question. So is being נעקר—is ne'ekar the moment that
the urine of a זבה zavah becomes טמא Tamei the moment of
עקירה akirah or the moment it comes out? And the גמרא Gemara
says it might not be the same as the question of when
the process begins by שכבת זרע shichvat zera for a man, because
there the עקירה akirah is more imminent to it coming out and
therefore a clearer part of the process than by the case of
urine. I do want to point out the irony, which is a
woman's טומאה tumah. is inside, בפנים, bifnim, but her urine might not
be טמא until it comes out outside. A man's טומאה tumah is
בחוץ, bachutz, only when the semen leaves the body, but for him
being נעקר, ne'ekar, when it's ready to come out, that might have
הלכה halacha significance for this aspect of הרגשה. hargashah So it's a
little bit flipped of what we normally say in terms of inside
versus outside.
Yes. Since women—since a
woman's menstrual period is as if she is a זבה
גדולה—right—would zavah gedolah
this have any implication for her being permitted to her husband or
is it just...?
No no no no no. All this stuff about urine and מעיינות,
mayanot, all this stuff, this is just about טומאה וטהרה. tumah ve-taharah.
Right? It has nothing to do—if she's once she's gone to the
מקוה mikvah. she is טהורה. tehorah. You speak about the urine like
you speak about the man's קרי and all of those things, that's
just a world of טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-taharah not a world of
personal status for נידה. Niddah. Okay, yes.
One question with this. So what you're saying with this זבה zavah
case is they're saying
even if she went to the bathroom right afterwards, right? Or are
they trying to say that meaning because she can hold it for
a while, she went to the bathroom two hours later maybe it's
different urine and not טמא?
No, the גמרא Gemara is not having a question about what urine
it was. That, I mean you could ask that question but that's
not the גמרא's Gemara question. The גמרא Gemara assumes that this was
the urine that was ready to come out when she went to
the מקוה. mikvah But the question was maybe the fact that it's
ready to come out doesn't have הלכה significance because it's not urgent,
it's not imminent, I should say, not urgent, it's not imminent. So
therefore it's not yet considered like urine because it hasn't come out
yet.
But she really really needs to go and...
Maybe. I mean you could theoretically make those types of distinctions. But
even without that, let's just ask the question before we get to
the such fine lines. And the גמרא Gemara doesn't know. תיקו. teiku.
Okay, so בעי ba'ei רבא: עובדת כוכבים זבה שנעקרו מימי רגליה. ovedet
kokhavim zavah she-ne'ekru memei raglehah.
A non-Jewish woman who is a זבה. zavah. Now we learned she's
a זבה. zavah. It means she's converted. So we really mean that
every non-Jewish woman has a status of a זבה zavah rabbinically, okay?
And therefore the urine of every non-Jewish woman would also be טמא.
So we're going to have the exact same question. She has to
go to the bathroom and now she's gone to the מקוה mikvah,
to become a Jew. Okay, so ויורדה, ve-yardah, she goes to the
מקוה, mikvah וטבלה. ve-tavlah. מה, mah, what do we say? אם תמצא
לומר im timtza lomar בתר עקירה אזלינן, batar akira azlinan, if we
go by the case of the woman who is a זבה zavah
by the עקירה akirah when it's uprooted and when she already needs
to go urinate, and we say that defines it as the—as urine
of a
זבה, zavah, that
it's טמא even from the moment she has to go. אף על
גב דמצי נקיט לה, af al gav de-matzi nakit lah, even though
she can hold it back, nevertheless since she has to go right
now, that's already considered urine of a זבה. zavah. הני מילי ישראלית,
hani milei Yisre'elit, fine, that's by a Jewish woman, דטומאה דאורייתא, de-tumah
de-oraita, that she's—that we're talking in a case where she's a זבה
zavah and it's biblical, and therefore the urine is a biblical status
of טמא, we would say that הלכה. We would go by from
the time she has to urinate. אבל עובדת כוכבים זבה דטומאה דרבנן,
aval ovedet kokhavim zavah de-tumah de-rabbanan, but the status of a non-Jewish
woman as a זבה zavah is only rabbinic. And therefore maybe we
wouldn't be so strict with her urine to define it from the
time she has to go and we would only define it when
it came out of her body. לא, we wouldn't be so strict.
או דילמא לא שנא, o dilma lo shanya, maybe we don't make
a difference. תיקו. teiku. And we don't have an answer. So we
had a lot of fascinating discussions there about the process of urinating
and the process of seminal emission, that there's two stages: when it
sort of becomes urgent and then when it's happened, and at what
stage is this thing considered to be part of the process and
significant. But more significantly of all of this, and that by the
way goes back also to the אביי ורבא's Abaye ve-Rava issue about
holding—holding yourself down, that there's a difference between when it's—when it's urgent
and when the process has begun than when it has not begun.
But what's most significant halakhically is the introduction of שמואל to this
concept that הרגשה matters by a man. It's not just that it
comes out of the body. At one stage it was about the
quality of the semen, his—his understanding that it could not inseminate. but
at another stage it was actually about the act of emission itself,
and the idea that it's not just objectively the semen, but it's
the way it comes out, and הרגשה is very significant here and
will be very significant by a similar case by women. Let's now
go to the last point of the משנה, Mishnah. which is that
the טומאה tumah of semen or blood is בכלשהו, bechol shehu, the
smallest amount. ומטמאים בכלשהו. U-metame'im bechol shehu. אמר שמואל, again שמואל, you
could see this was a topic that שמואל was very involved in.
I'm serious, some אמוראים Amoraim focus more on certain topics than others.
זב צריך כחתימת פי האמה. zav tzarich ke-chatimat pi ha-amah. It's by
a זב as opposed to maybe a woman and the blood or
maybe a man who's a בעל קרי, although he's not clear about
the בעל קרי, at least by a זב it has to be
a flow that completely fills the orifice, the orifice of the hole
of the penis, שנאמר as the פסוק pasuk says, או החתים בשרו
מזובו, O hechtim besaro mi-zovo, or his flesh is filled, is sealed
through the flow. So meaning it has to fill the orifice. והנן
תנן Ve-hanan tenan מטמאים בכלשהו, metame'im bechol shehu, doesn't our משנה Mishnah,
say even the smallest amount? And that's including a זב and a
זבה, zavah, basically mentions all of the flows of men and women.
So he says you're right, he doesn't go like our משנה. Mishnah.
There's another ברייתא braita he goes like. הוא דאמר כרבי נתן, Hu
de-amar ke-Rabbi Natan, he goes like רבי נתן, Rabbi Natan, דתניא, di-tanya,
we learn in the ברייתא, braita, רבי נתן אומר משום רבי ישמעאל,
Rabbi Natan omer mishum Rabbi Yishmael, in the name of רבי ישמעאל,
Rabbi Yishmael, זב צריך כחתימת פי האמה. tzarich ke-chatimat pi ha-amah. A
זב, the flow has to fill the orifice, the hole. ולא הודו
לו, Ve-lo hodu lo, they didn't agree to him. But not clear
what he would say about a בעל קרי, but at least a
זב needs חתימת פי האמה. chatimat pi ha-amah. מאי טעמא דרבי ישמעאל?
Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Yishmael? What's the reason? דאמר קרא, the פסוק pasuk.
says או החתים. o hechtim. או החתים בשרו מזובו. O hechtim besaro
mi-zovo. It says that it literally, the flow, the flesh is sealed
through the flow, which means that the flow fills up the hole.
ורבנן, Ve-rabbanan, the rabbis would say no. ההוא מבעי ליה ללח מטמא
ואינו מטמא יבש. Hahu mibayei lei le-lach metame ve-eino metame yavesh. That's
to tell you only when the flow comes out as a liquid,
because a liquid can seal a hole, and not when it comes
out like solid. I don't know how it would come out solid,
but maybe when it also dries later it doesn't cause טומאה Tumah
unless it's in a state where it could fill something, which is
meaning a liquid state. ורבי ישמעאל Ve-Rabbi Yishmael says ההוא מריר נפקא.
hahu me-rar nafka. I learn it from the פסוק pasuk where it
says ריר, rar, which means like literally it is like dribbling. So
that already just describes the quality of it as a liquid. החתים
Hechtim calls for it had to fill the hole. ורבנן, Ve-rabbanan, ההוא
למניינא הוא דאתא. hahu le-minyana hu de-ata. The ריר rar is to
give me a number. Meaning,
as we know, a זב two times he sees he's טמא for
seven days, three times he brings a
קרבן, korban,
and we learn out those numbers two and three times
from the number of ways the תורה describes the flow, the various
words it uses. So the rabbis say that's just to help me
count to the number to get up to three. Yeah, but if
it's just a count it could've used the same verb. I understand.
So זובו חדא, zovo chada, ריר בשרו. rar besaro. So this is
quoting the פסוק. pasuk It says זאת תהיה טומאתו בזובו, Zot tihyeh
tumato bi-zovo, this is his טומאה Tumah in his flow, flow is
one. ריר בשרו, Rar besaro, the flesh dribbles, that's two. תרי. trei.
את זובו, Et zovo, his flow, three. תלת. tlat. Plus. So I
need it to get me a count. לימד על זב בעל שלוש
ראיות שחייב בקרבן, Limed al zav ba'al shalosh re'iyot she-chayav be-korban, when
he sees three times, two times he's טמא seven days, three times
he already brings a קרבן. korban. או החתים בשרו מזובו, O hechtim
besaro mi-zovo, or his flesh is filled from the flow. טמא, he's
טמא. So it's מזובו, mi-zovo, from the flow. מקצת זובו טמא. Mikzat
zovo tame. Even part of the flow, not three times causes טומאה.
Tumah לימד על זב בעל שתי ראיות שמטמא משכב ומושב. Limed al
zav ba'al shtei re'iyot she-metame mishkav u-moshav. So even if it's twice,
then he's seven day טומאה, everything he sits on is טמא, but
it does not a קרבן. korban. That's how he learns the פסוקים,
pesukim but in the end of the day, not to tell me
that it has to fill the hole. ורבי ישמעאל, Ve-Rabbi Yishmael, מניינא
מנא ליה? minyana mena leh? Where does רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael know
the count to three? So he could've thought like Michael that yes
he counts the same count but the use of the word ריר
rar still tells me flow, but let's see what he says. נפקא
ליה מרבי סימאי. Nafka leh me-Rabbi Simai. He learns from רבי סימאי.
Rabbi Simai. דתניא רבי סימאי אומר, De-tanya Rabbi Simai omer, מנה הכתוב
שתיים וקראו טמא, mana ha-katuv shtayim ve-kera'o tame, שלוש וקראו טמא. shalosh
ve-kera'o tame. So the תורה says twice it's a flow and it
says טמא and three times a flow and it says טמא. הכיצד?
Ha-keitzad? So what does, how do you learn that from? So שתיים
לטומאה ושלוש לקרבן. shtayim le-tumah ve-shalosh le-korban. Two for טומאה and three
for קרבן. korban. Meaning basically he learns it from other words. If
you look רש"י Rashi says it. שתיים וקראו טמא. Shtayim ve-kera'o tame.
רש"י Rashi says about six lines down in the narrow lines, ריר
בשרו מזובו rar besaro mi-zovo חדא, chada, זובו טמא zovo tame תרי.
trei. And instead it says זאת תהיה טומאתו בזובו Zot tihyeh tumato
bi-zovo חדא, chada, ריר בשרו rar besaro תרי, trei, או החתים בשרו
מזובו o hechtim besaro mi-zovo תלת. tlat. תורת זו? Torat zo? He
actually, so in the end I'm just looking רש"י Rashi again. He
actually does say like Michael that yes from the ריר בשרו rar
besaro he does. It's actually funny that it quotes רבי Reb סימאי.
Simai. At the end of the day it's saying yes he does
a similar count, he gets to two and three, but somehow he
still has the פסוק pasuk. left over of החתים hechtim to tell
me that it has to fill and that it has to show
the orifice in order to be a problem. Yes, two and three
same word like a woman's זבה? zavah? No, by a woman it
is three consecutive days, by a זב it is even within those
like the days? Yeah, no. Right, a woman, if it's three ראיות
re'iyos on the same day, it doesn't count. It has to be
three ראיות re'iyos on three separate days. A זב, it does not
need to be, it could be three all at once. You're saying,
can it be, how far can it be spread out? I assume
that if you go to the מקוה mikvah, between the first one
and you're done with the טומאה, then it doesn't combine. But if
you haven't gone to the מקוה, then it could be indefinite. I'd
have to check, I'm pretty sure. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara.
says, anyway, so fine, he learned it from a similar count, but
it's not, but he's not bothered with each of the Rabbis. So
the Rabbis, at the end of the day, the Rabbis say that
we're learning from the פסוקים the number and והחתים vehechtim sealing is
just telling me a flow, a liquid. And רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
says, I learn from רר rar liquid and I learn from החתים
hechtim that it has to fill the orifice. And now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, ולמאן דנפקא ליה תרוייהו מזאת תהיה טומאתו בזובו.
uleman denafkah lei tarvaihu mizot tihyeh tumato bezovo. So there's another opinion
that learns all the laws of two and three and the number
of times from the פסוק pasuk of זאת תהיה טומאתו בזובו, zot
tihyeh tumato bezovo, a different פסוק. pasuk איש איש כי יהיה זב
מבשרו, ish ish ki yihyeh zav mibesaro, מאי עביד ליה? mai avid
lei? What does he do with the פסוק pasuk that we've been
דרשן-ing darshan up until now? So מיבעי ליה עד שיצא מבשרו, mibaei
lei ad sheyetzei mibesaro, that, well, what we've said before now, which
is the basic הלכה that it has to be מבשרו, mibesaro, it
has to leave his flesh. It's not internal, it's only when it
exits his body. Did anyone read that? Yeah. So it's not going
to, frankly, it's not going to work out how you get every
single דרשה. drasha. So let's not work it out either. זובו טמא
למה לי? zovo tamei lamah li? And why do you need the
next part of the verse that says his flow is tamei? For
literally to tell you פשט, pshat, ללמד על הזוב שהוא טמא, lelamed
al hazov shehu tamei, that the very flow itself is טמא. Not
only is the person טמא, but the fluid itself is טמא. So
basically what do we learn? From the fact that the תורה says
all these extra words, רר בשרו את זובו, rar besaro et zovo,
etc., etc., we learn the idea two times and three times. From,
we also learn the idea it has to be a fluid, not
a solid. It has to be like, you know, in a liquid
state, רר rar or החתים. hechtim. And we learn the idea that
it has to leave the body, מבשרו. mibesaro. We learn that the
fluid, the liquid itself is טמא, זובו טמא. zovo tamei. And the
one thing we debate is whether it has to fill the orifice.
Do we learn it from that פסוק pasuk of החתים בשרו hechtim
besaro that only when there's enough to fill the orifice? When we
say the liquid thing, that's the way it came out. But like,
you know, if you touch it a few days later... No, the
fluid's טומאה also, I'll double check, but I think that's the later
משנה, Mishnah. is that the damp things, you know, once they dry
up, do not conduct טומאה anymore. We'll see that in a משנה.
Mishnah אמר רב חנילאי משום רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Amar Rav Chanilai
mishum Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon. Yeah, we'll see it, it's a big,
there's a list of which ones yes, which ones no. אמר רב
חנילאי משום רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Amar Rav Chanilai mishum Rabbi Elazar
berabi Shimon. Okay, so now that we've done a whole discussion of
the דרשות, drashot, let's get to the הלכה, let's get to sort
of more discussing the הלכה per se. So we've discussed the זיבה
zivah whether that has to fill the hole. So now רב חנילאי
Rav Chanilai says in the name of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi
Elazar berabi Shimon, שכבת זרע לרואה בכל שהוא לנוגע בכעדשה. shichvat zera
laro'eh bechol shehu lanogei kikeadashah. Whatever you say about זב, and we're
not, he's not addressing that, when it comes to semen, so if
it comes out of the man's body even a tiniest drop, even
if it doesn't fill the hole, I don't even know how that's
possible, but even if it's a tiniest drop it causes him to
be טמא. But when it's the טומאה of touching it, that needs
a minimum size. That needs a size of a lentil, being that's
the amount of size that normally a שרץ, sheretz, a dead rodent
is, and we're going to learn it from a פסוק pasuk of
שרץ. sheretz. If you remember the גמרא when it discusses the difference
of is a certain thing רואה or נוגע? Is it about what
happens to your body or is it about touching? A question we
had about a woman when the זרע comes, when the שכבת זרע
shichvat zera, comes from her, as a man when he has שכבת
זרע, shichvat zera the classic נפקא מינה nafka mina the גמרא has
is the שיעור. shiur. If it's about, if there's a minimum שיעור,
shiur, then it's about conducting it from the outside and the thing,
as a thing, has to have significance. Okay? If it's about what
happens to your body, even without a minimum שיעור, shiur, it's not
a focus on the thing as the source of what makes you
טמא. And here he says that explicitly. When it happens to the
man, when it comes out from the man, that man is even
the smallest amount. But if somebody else touches semen, then it's about
conducting it from the thing, and the thing has to have significance,
and only when it's a minimum size. But all in one place,
or... Right, yeah, all in one place. So now let's take a
look where he gets this from. Okay, we can get to the
משנה. והאנן מטמאי בכל שהוא תנן. vahanan metamei bechol shehu tenan. Doesn't
our משנה say the smallest amount? מאי לאו לנוגע? mai lav lanogei?
Doesn't it mean even to conduct by touching? לא לרואה. lo laro'eh.
No, it means when it happens to your body. It doesn't mean
from somebody else touching it. תא שמע, come in here. חומר בשכבת
זרע מבשרץ וחומר בשרץ מבשכבת זרע. chomer beshichvat zera mibsheretz vechomer besheretz
mibshichvat zera. There are ways in which semen is more strict than
the טומאה of a dead rodent and some ways the rodent more
than the semen. חומר בשרץ שהשרץ אין חלוקה טומאתו. chomer besheretz shehasheretz
ein chalukah tumato. The way the rodent is more strict, for the
rodent, there's no distinction. All dead rodents are טמא. I mean, not
all dead rodents, actually it's not true, only eight of them, but
when you are in the category, there's no distinction between like which
type of a rat or another type. מה שאין כן בשכבת זרע.
ma she'ein ken beshichvat zera. As opposed to the semen. What does
that mean? So basically what the גמרא's going to say it means
is that only שכבת זרע shichvat zera from a somebody who is
nine years old and a day. But if you were to have
שכבת זרע shichvas zera from a, yeah, you could, actually you could
have said that before. when it's not ראוי להזריע rauy lehazria and
when it's whatever. But that's not what he's gonna say, it's gonna
say when it comes from a boy under nine years old, then
it is not טמא, whereas if you have a rodent that's a
young rodent or an old rodent it doesn't matter. All right, that's
not a big difference, but that's at least listed as the way
that the שרץ sheretz is more strict. Where are we? חומר בשכבת
זרע חומר בשכבת זרע Okay, חומר בשכבת זרע now the semen is
more strict that שכבת זרע מטמא בכל שהוא shichvas zera metamei bechol
shehu even the smallest amount. מה שאין כן בשרץ. ma she'ein ken
besheretz. Now בשרץ besheretz a שרץ sheretz is כעדשה ke'adasha the size
of a bean. So מאי לאו? mai lav? So it says, it's
comparing the semen to the rodent. Presumably it means touching the rodent,
touching the semen. מאי לאו בנוגע? mai lav benogea? Don't we mean
touching and it says even the smallest amount? לאו לרואה. lav leroeh.
No, it means when it comes out of your body. הא דומיא
דשרץ קתני. ha dumya desheretz katani. But we're comparing it to the
rodent. מה שרץ בנגיעה אף שכבת זרע בנגיעה. ma sheretz benegiah af
shichvas zera benegiah. So the same way you get טמא by the
rodent is by touching it, we're talking about presumably touching the semen
and we're saying it's בכל שהוא. bechol shehu. The גמרא says, אמר
רב אדא בר אהבה, amar Rav Adda bar Ahava, no. שום שרץ
קתני ושום שכבת זרע קתני. shum sheretz katani veshum shichvas zera katani.
We're not talking about the exact same case. We say there are
ways in which semen is more strict because when it comes from
your body, it's בכל שהוא bechol shehu not in the analogous case.
In the analogous case, it is the same הלכה, you need the
size of a bean. But there are ways in which semen is
more strict in a non-analogous case when it comes from your body.
Even with the bean thing, if it's a בריה biryah then it
could be less than. We're gonna get to it. השרץ אינו מטמא
במשהו? hasheretz eino metamei bemashehu? Michael once again anticipates the גמרא. Are
you telling me that a rodent cannot be, cannot have a case
of even a small piece of a rodent? והתנן, vehatnan, we taught.
אברים אין להם שיעור evarim ein lahem shiur that if you have
a limb of something, it doesn't matter how tiny it is. פחות
מכזית מבשר המת, pachos mikizayis mibesar hames, if you have less than
a כזית kezayis of flesh of a dead body, human body, if
it's actually a whole limb like a tiny pinky or something of
a... or פחות מכזית מבשר נבלה pachos mikizayis mibesar neveilah or less
than a כזית kezayis from the flesh of a dead animal corpse,
if it's a whole limb, it will cause טומאה. ופחות מכעדשה מן
השרץ upachos mike'adasha min hasheretz and less than the size of a
bean from a שרץ, sheretz, if it's an entire limb from a
rodent it causes טומאה. So you see there's ways in which a
שרץ sheretz is also בכל שהוא. bechol shehu. What do you mean
a שרץ sheretz isn't a בכל שהוא? bechol shehu? The גמרא says,
okay, שאני אבר דכוליה במקום עדשה קאי. shani eiver dechulei bimkom adasha
kai. That's not a בכל שהוא. bechol shehu. Yes, you can't say
a שרץ sheretz is also a בכל שהוא bechol shehu because when
you have a limb, a limb is a substitute for a significant
size. Right? Quantity versus something having significance. Quantity and quality. When we
say it has to be the size of a lentil bean, we're
talking about a certain quantity gives it significance. When you say בכל
שהוא bechol shehu you're saying it doesn't need significance. The reason an
אבר eiver is מטמא בכל שהוא metamei bechol shehu is because that's
a substitute, a form of being significant. It's like it's the right
size. It's another way of being significant. Okay? דכוליה במקום עדשה קאי
דהא אילו חסר פורתא דאבר, dechulei bimkom adasha kai deha ilu chasar
purta de'eiver, if you're missing part of a limb, מי קא מטמא?
mi ka metamei? It would not be טמא. So there still is
a difference. Semen still causes טומאה with no significance, with a בכל
שהוא, bechol shehu, where שרץ sheretz needs either quantitative or qualitative. Okay.
So therefore now we've finished discussing this ברייתא, beraisa, so we're not
really able to contradict and we still have the statement that when
it comes from the body it's בכל שהוא, bechol shehu, when you
touch it it's the size of a bean. Now שכבת זרע דחלוקה
טומאתו מאי? shichvas zera dechaluka tumaso mai? What does it mean there
are ways in which the semen is טמא and ways in which
it's not? Sometimes yes, sometimes no. אילימא בן ישראל לדהנכרים, eileima ben
yisrael lidenochrim, semen of a Jew versus a non-Jew? So הא נמי
איכא עכבר דימא ועכבר דיבשה. ha nami ika achbar deyama ve'achbar deyabasha.
So so what? There are some rodents that are טמא and some
that are not טמא. So that's what I mean, so you could
say a Jew's שכבת זרע Shikhvat Zera. versus a non-Jew's, so same
is true by rodents. Even sometimes the rodent with a similar name,
there was something that they called a sea rat. Okay, whatever it
was. Anyway, so then it's not different than rodents that way. אלא
בין קטן לגדול. ela bein katan legadol. Okay, what I told you
before. Semen of an adult versus semen of a minor as opposed
to a שרץ sheretz it doesn't matter how old the שרץ sheretz
is. Fine. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, going back to our
earlier point, כתנאי. ketannai. This issue about do you need a minimum
amount of, when you touch semen to become טמא is a debate
of תנאים. tannaim. Here's the, here's the ברייתא: beraisa: מנין לרבות נוגע
בשכבת זרע? minayin lerabos nogea beshichvas zera? How do you know touching
semen causes טומאה in addition to coming out of the body? תלמוד
לומר או איש. talmud lomar o ish. Okay, now so what does
it mean או איש? o ish? So we assume this is the
פסוק Pasuk by touching a שרץ. sheretz. Okay, או איש אשר יצא
ממנו? o ish asher yeitzei mimenu? I know, that's the first thing
I thought of. So but רש"י says there's also או אשר יגע
בכל שרץ אשר יטמא לו. o asher yiga bechol sheretz asher yitma
lo. So we assume that we're learning touching semen from a פסוק
Pasuk of touching a שרץ. sheretz. And therefore he says that would
exactly lead to the debate of is there a minimum size. How
would it lead to a debate? ופליגי תנאי בעלמא, uphligi tannai be'alma,
there's a general debate of תנאים, tannaim, דאיכא דאמרי דון מינה ומינה,
de'ika de'amri don minah uminah, learn from it and with it, ואיכא
דאמרי דון מינה ואוקי באתרה, ve'ika de'amri don minah ve'okei be'asrah, learn
from it and put it in its context. When you learn a
הלכה, there's A and B. You're learning a הלכה from A that's
relevant to B. Do we contain, when we apply it to B,
do we give it the context of A? Or do we now
transplanted and give it the context of B. So we're learning from
the פרשת שרץ Parshat Sheretz that there's טומאה of שכבת זרע. Shikhvat
Zera, So do we contain it within the context of שרץ? Sheretz?
שרץ Sheretz is a minimum size of a כעדשה. Ke'adashah. So the
semen also will be that size even when we now apply it
into the semen category, it retains that context דנו מיניה וביה. Dano
Minei Ubei. Or do we put it in the relevant context of
semen? and semen normally when it comes from the body is a
כל שהוא, Kol Shehu, so when you touch it it will also
be a כל שהוא. Kol Shehu. That's how he wants to understand
you can get both opinions. You learn it from שכבת זרע, Shikhvat
Zera if you apply the context of שכבת זרע Shikhvat Zera. or
do you apply the context of semen? למאן דאמר דנו מיניה וביה,
Le-man De-amar Dano Minei Ubei, if you learn from it and keep
the context, מה שרץ בנגיעה שכבת זרע בנגיעה. Mah Sheretz Be-negiah Shikhvat
Zera Be-negiah. So the first thing you can get is this: you
come טמא by touching a שרץ, Sheretz, you become טמא by touching
semen. ומיניה, U-minei, and now keep the context. מה שרץ בכעדשה, Mah
Sheretz Be-ke'adashah, a שרץ Sheretz is only needs the minimum size of
a bean, אף שכבת זרע בכעדשה, Af Shikhvat Zera Be-ke'adashah, same by
the semen. ולמאן דאמר דנו מיניה ואוקמה באתריה, U-le-man De-amar Dano Minei
Ve-ukmei Be-atrei, and according to the one that says you learn from
it but then you put it in its natural context, so what
do we learn? The learning is מה שרץ בנגיעה שכבת זרע בנגיעה.
Mah Sheretz Be-negiah Shikhvat Zera Be-negiah. A שרץ Sheretz you get טמא
by touching, same by semen. ואוקמה באתריה, Ve-ukmei Be-atrei, but now put
it in its natural context. מה שכבת זרע לראיה במשהו, Mah Shikhvat
Zera Le-reiyah Be-mashehu, the same way semen when it comes out of
the body is a משהו, Mashehu, אף נוגע במשהו, Af No-geia Be-mashehu,
even when you touch it. So he says, I think it's a
debate of תנאים. Tanna'im. Once you learn it from the פסוק Pasuk
of שרץ, Sheretz, then there will be naturally a debate whether you
apply the context of שרץ Sheretz or do you apply the context
of שכבת זרע. Shikhvat Zera אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב נתן
לרב פפא, Amar Lei Rav Huna Brei De-rav Natan Le-rav Pappa, so
the response came back to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, ממאי דמאו איש
דשרץ קמרבי ליה? Mimmai De-me-o Ish De-sheretz Kamarbi Lei? Why do you
think they're learning from the פסוק Pasuk about שרץ Sheretz and then
you could say we're debating whether to keep that context or not?
דילמא מאו איש אשר תצא ממנו שכבת זרע קמרבי ליה, Dilma Me-o
Ish Asher Tetzei Mimmenu Shikhvat Zera Kamarbi Lei, which is the פסוק
Pasuk both Michael and I thought of right off the top. Maybe
it's the פסוק from שכבת זרע Shikhvat Zera. itself, there's an extra
word of או איש, O Ish, and that tells you even another
form of טומאה of שכבת זרע. Shikhvat Zera, ודכולי עלמא דנו מיניה
וביה, U-de-kuli Alma Dano Minei Ubei, and everybody will say you can
learn it from its original context. Even if you keep its original
context, but the original context is שכבת זרע, Shikhvat Zera so it
would remain to be a כל שהוא. Kol Shehu. So if you're
not learning it from שרץ, Sheretz, then everybody would agree it would
be a כל שהוא. Kol Shehu. שאלנוהו לתנאי, She'alinhu Le-tana'ei, they asked
the תנאים. Tanna'im. תנאים Tanna'im here means the repeaters, those that had
memorized this ברייתא, Baraita, because they all had taught a ברייתא Baraita
that we learn touching שכבת זרע Shikhvat Zera. from the פסוק of
או איש. O Ish. So they said to them: Which או איש
O Ish did you mean? Okay, so they asked the people that
had memorized it. איכא דתני כרב פפא ואיכא דתני כרב הונא בריה
דרב נתן. Ika De-tani Ke-rav Pappa Ve-ika De-tani Ke-rav Huna Brei De-rav
Natan. So some said we meant the או איש O Ish of
the שרץ, Sheretz, and others said we meant the או איש O
Ish of the שכבת זרע. Shikhvat Zera So in the end, we
don't know. We know that when שכבת זרע comes from the body,
it's a כל שהוא. Kol Shehu. When you touch it, there are
some that say like the body, כל שהוא, Kol Shehu, and some
that say no, like any other טומאה that's conducted from the outside,
there needs to be significant in the object and it needs a
שיעור Shiur and the amount of a כעדשה. Ke'adashah. Okay.